In this video, we will be talking about
the
right-hand rule and how to actually use
it.
First of all, what is the right-hand rule?
The
right-hand rule is a rule that works for
positively
charged particles that can determine
either
its field, motion, or current, and by
field,
magnetic field. The motion is the force
being
exerted. A magnetic field with a current
always
exerts a force on a charged object.
However, it is important to note that the
right-hand
rule only works for positively charged
particles.
However, if you want to use it for
negatively
charged particles, you would have to
reverse
the direction of the motion.
So, if you use your right-hand rule and
you
got the motion would be going to the
right,
then for an electron, it would be going to
the
other side. This is because the force of a
charged
particle is given by qvb, where q is the
charge
of the particle, b is the magnetic field,
and
v is the velocity. But as you can see, if
charge
is negative, the force would be in a
different
direction because it's a vector. So, let's
have
this question over here. And we want to
determine
the direction a positively charged
particle
would be going if it was brought near a
wire.
Now, first of all, what do these dots
mean?
Well, these dots represent the direction
of
the magnetic field. X's represent when the
magnetic
field is pointing into the page, while
dots
are representing the magnetic field
pointing
out of the page. So actually, the magnetic
field
is kind of going around in a circle.
But if the particle is above, then it's
going
to be within the magnetic field part that
is
pointing out of the page. Let's say the
current
is going towards the right. So we have a
going towards the right, and since the
particle
is above the wire, it's going to be having
a
magnetic field pointing out of the page.
So
what we want to do is we want to match the
current
with our middle finger towards the right,
the
field pointing out of the page, and we
would
get that the motion would be going
upwards.
So this would be going upwards.
However, for an electron, it is different
because
we can't use the magnetic right hand rule.
We could either first switch it to a
positively
charged particle.
We could either switch it to a positively
charged
particle, or we could use our left hand
rule.
Because when we use our left hand, the
motion
will be switched. So either use right hand
rule
on a positive, and then reverse it, or
just
use your other hand. Let's try using our
other
hand. We would point our index finger out
of
the page, and then the current to the
right.
So we would have our force pointed
downwards.
And as you can see, it's the exact
opposite
as what a positively charged particle
would
do. Another way to use our right hand rule
is
to use this. And the palm would be
representing
the direction of the force, the fingers
would
be representing the direction of the
field,
and the thumb would be representing the
direction
of the current. In a solenoid, it is very
different.
A solenoid is basically a wire wrapped
around
in a circle. And our right hand grip rule
actually
governs the force. When you wrap your
fingers
around the direction of the current of the
solenoid,
your thumb will be pointing towards the
force
of the thing.
So for example, if we would have a
positively
charged object inside the solenoid, it
would
have a force going towards the left in
this
case. And that's it for right hand rules.
Another tip of advice is right hand rule
is
very easy to grasp the concept, but in
order
to be good at it, you need a lot, a lot of
practice.
So the number one key thing to mastering
the
right hand rule, and magnetism in general,
is
just to find a lot of practice questions
and
be able to do these really, really
quickly.
Thank you for watching, and I hope you
found
this video helpful. Bye.